Guide to the Charles Reade Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Charles Reade collection
1863-1874
GEN MSS 124
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.2
(2 boxes)
Letters by Charles Reade to various parties, including Wilkie Collins, Harper & Brothers, and Jenny Lind, with one letter to Reade from James Ripley Osgood. Manuscripts of "Christie Johnstone," "An Egoist," "A Hero and a Martyr," and "Singleheart and double-face."
Reade, Charles, 1814-1884
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Charles Reade, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to June 1997 have been organized into 2 series: Writings and Correspondence.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Collins, Wilkie, 1824-1889; Lind, Jenny, 1820-1887; Osgood, Charles Ripley; Reade, Charles, 1814-1884; Harper & Brothers
- Manuscripts, n.d.; Series I
  - "Christie Johnstone: a play in three acts", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Manuscript in an unidentified hand with corrections and additions in hand of the author; Gift, 1973.
  - "An Egoist", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Autograph manuscript, signed, with corrections and additions in the author's hand; Gift, 1973.
  - "A Hero and a Martyr" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Autograph manuscript of an essay on James Lambert; Reade's "Notes on James Lambert" removed from a notebook, inlaid to folio, and bound with the above; Published in the Pall Mall Gazette, 1874 Nov 25, 26, 28, 29; Gift, 1957.
  - "Singleheart and double-face".
    Original Holograph manuscript; the first chapter and one leaf are wanting; Autograph signature of Charles Reade on last leaf; Tipped in: ALS to B. Webster, esq. [London] 1881? Feb 27 Gift, 1931.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Oversize, Box 2, folder 18
- Correspondence, Series II
  - OSGOOD, JAMES RIPLEY, 1836-92.
    - ALS to Charles Reade. Boston, 1871 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Purchase, 1947.
  - READE, CHARLES
    - ALS to B. Webster, esq. [London], 1881? Feb 27
      See: Series I. "Singleheart and double-face"
    - ALS to Sir Edwin Arnold. Cannes, 1884 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Endorsed: "The last letter penned by my dear friend. E. A." Gift, 1970.
    - ALS to Andrew Chatto. Edinburgh, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Concerning the Reade-Glasgow Herald suit over his "A Hero and a martyr, 1874; Purchase, 1957.
    - ALS to Wilkie Collins. London. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Purchase, 1958.
    - 22 letters (including 7 copies of letters) and 2 telegrams to Harper & Brothers, firm, publishers, New York. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to "Hume"[?]. Knightsbridge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Miss Leclerq. Knightsbridge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to Jenny Lind. Knightsbridge (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Gift, 1956.
    - ALS (Copy) to Sheldon & Co. [London], 1872 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      On verso of page 3: copy of letter Harper & Brothers to Sheldon & Co., 1872 Apr 8; Purchase, 1947.
    - ALS to Mr. Vaughan, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to a publisher [Pall Mall Gazette?]. Knightsbridge, 1874? Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Heroes and Martyrs, mentioned in this letter, appeared in the Pall Mall Gazette in 1874 Nov; Purchase, 1956.
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient. Mayfair, 1863 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 3 ALS to unidentified recipients. Knightsbridge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient. Knightsbridge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Gift, 1955.
- Oversize, n.d.
  - Manuscripts - "Singleheart and double-face". (Box 2, Folder 18)